[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
today i'm talking to alexander pugh he's
a solutions architect with over five
years of experience working on robotic
process automation and cognitive
services today we're going to focus on
robotic process automation
alexander welcome to software
engineering radio thank you jeremy it's
really good to be here so what does
robotic process automation actually mean
it's a very broad nebulous term when we
talk about robotic process automation as
a concept we're talking about
automating
things that
humans do
in the way that they do them so that's
the robotic
and automation that is done in the way a
human does a thing and then process is
that thing
that we're automating and then
automation is saying we're turning this
into an automation we're orchestrating
this and automating this and the best
way to think about that
in any other way is to think of a
factory or a car assembly line
so initially when we went in and we
automated a car or factory automation
line what they did is essentially they
replicated the
process as a human did it so one day you
had a human that would pick up a door
and then put it on the car and bolt it
on with their arms and so the initial
automations that we had on those factory
lines were a robot arm that would pick
up that door from the same place and put
it on the car and bolt it on there so
the same can be said for robotic process
automation we're essentially looking at
these
processes that humans do and we're
replicating them with an automation that
doesn't in the same way and where we're
doing that is the operating system so
robotic process automation is
essentially going in and automating the
operating system to perform tasks the
same way a human would do them in an
operating system so that's rpa in a
nutshell so when you say you're
replicating something that a human would
do does it mean it has to go through
some kind of gui or some kind of user
interface that's exactly right actually
when we're talking about rpa and we look
at a process that we want to automate
with rpa we say okay let's watch the
human do it let's record that let's
document the human process and then
let's
use the rpa tool to
replicate that exactly in that way so go
double click on
chrome
launch that click in the
url line and send key in
www.cnn.com or what have you or
servicenow hit enter wait for it to load
and then
click you know where you want to you
know fill out your ticket for service
now send key in so that's exactly
how our pa solution at the most basic
can be achieved now and any software
engineer knows if you sit there and look
over someone's shoulder and watch them
use an operating system you'll say well
there's a lot of ways we can do this
more efficiently without going over here
clicking that you know we can
use a lot of services that the operating
system provides in a programmatic way to
achieve the same ends and rpa solutions
can also do that the
real key
is making sure that it is still
achieving something that the human does
and
that if the
rpa solution goes away a human can still
achieve it so if you're trying to
replace or replicate a process with rpa
you don't want to change that process so
much so
that a human can no longer achieve it as
well that's something where if you get a
very technical and very fluent software
engineer they lose sight of that because
they say oh you know what there's no
reason why we need to go open a browser
and go to you know the servicenow portal
and type this in when i can just
directly send information to their
backend which a human cannot replicate
right so that's kind of where the line
gets fuzzy how efficiently can we make
this rpa solution i think a question
that a lot of people are probably having
is a lot of applications have apis now
but what you're saying is that for it to
be i suppose true rpa it needs to be
something that a user can do on their
own and not something that the user can
do by opening up dev tools or making a
post to an endpoint yeah and so it's
probably really important right now to
talk about why rpa right why would you
do this when you could put on a server a
really good api ingestion point or
trigger or a web hook that can do this
stuff so why would we ever pursue our pa
there's a lot of good reasons for it rpa
is very very
enticing to the business
rpa solutions and tools are marketed as
a
low code no code solution for the
business to utilize to solve their
processes that may not be solved by an
enterprise solution in the in between
processes in a way
you have a big enterprise finance
solution that everyone uses for the
finance needs of your business but there
are some things that it doesn't provide
for that you have a person that's doing
a lot of and the business says okay well
this thing this human is doing this is
really beneath their capability
we need to get a software solution for
it but our enterprise solution just
can't account for it so let's get
a rpa capability in here we can build it
ourselves and then
there we go so there are many reasons to
do that financial it might not have the
capability or the funding to actually
build and solve the solution
or it's at a scale that is
too small to open up an i.t project to
solve for so you know a team of five is
just doing this and they're doing it for
you know 20 hours a week which is
large but in a big enterprise that's not
really maybe worth building an
enterprise solution for it or and this
is a big one there are regulatory
constraints and security constraints
around being able to access this or
communicate some data or information
in a way that is
non-human or programmatic so that's
really where
rpa is
correctly and best applied and you'll
see it most often so what we're talking
about there is in finance in healthcare
or in big
companies
where they're dealing with a lot of user
data or customer data in a way so when
we talk about finance and health care
there are a lot of regulatory
constraints
and security reasons why you would not
enable a programmatic solution
to
operate on
your systems you know it's just too hard
we're not going to expose our databases
or our data to any other thing it would
take a huge enterprise project to build
out that capability secure that
capability and ensure it's going
correctly we just don't have the money
the time or or the strength honestly
to afford for it so they say well
we already have a user pattern we
already allow users to talk to this
information and communicate this
information
let's get an rpa tool which for all
intents purposes will be acting as a
user
and then it can just automate that
process without us exposing
to queries or
any other thing
in an enterprise solution or
programmatic solution so that's really
why rpa where and why you would apply it
is there's just no capability at
enterprise for one reason or another to
solve for it as software engineers when
we see this kind of problem our first
thought is okay let's build this custom
application or workflow that's going to
talk to all these apis and what it
sounds like is
in a lot of cases
there just isn't the time there just
isn't the money to put in the effort to
do that
and it also sounds like this is a way of
being able to automate that
and maybe introducing less risk because
you're going through the same
security
the same workflow that
people are doing currently so you know
you're not going to get into things that
they're not supposed to be able to get
into because all of that's already put
in place
correct and it's an already accepted
pattern and it's kind of odd to apply
that kind of very i t software engineer
term
to a human
user but a human user is a pattern
in software engineering we have patterns
that do this and that and you know
databases and not and then the user
journey or the user permissions and
security and all that is a pattern and
that is
accepted by default when you're building
these enterprise applications okay
what's the user pattern and so since
that's already established and well
known and all the hopefully
you know walls are built around that to
enable it to correctly do what it needs
to do it's saying okay we've already
established let's just use that instead
of
you know building a programmatic
solution where we have to go and find do
we already have an appropriate pattern
to apply to it can we build it in a safe
way and then can we support it all of a
sudden you know we have these support
teams that watch our splunk dashboards
and make sure nothing's going down with
our big enterprise application
and then you're going to build a another
capability okay where's that support
going to come from and now we got to
talk about change access boards user
testing and
you know uat dev
production environments and all that so
it becomes
untenable depending on your organization
to do that for things that might fall
into a place that is
it doesn't justify
the scale that needs to be thrown upon
it but when we talk about something like
apis and apis exist for a lot of things
they don't exist for everything and a
lot of times that's for
legacy databases that's for mainframe
capability and this is really where
rpa shines and is correctly applied and
especially in big businesses or highly
regulated businesses where they can't
upgrade to the newest thing or they
can't throw something into the cloud
they have you know their mainframe
systems or they have their database
systems
that have to exist for one reason or the
other
until
there is
the motivation and the money and the
time to correctly migrate and solve for
them so until that day
again there's no
api to do anything on a mainframe in
this bank or whatnot it's like well okay
let's just throw our pa on it let's you
know let's have our pa do this thing
in the way that a human does it but it
can do it 24 7. an example or a use case
is you work at a bank and there's no way
that infosec is going to let you query
against this database with
your users that have this account or
your customers that have this
no way in any organization at a bank is
infosec going to say oh yeah sure let me
give you an odata query you know driver
on you know and you can just set up your
own sql queries and do whatever they're
going to say no way in fact how did you
find out about this database in the
first place
and who are you how do we solve it we go
and say okay how does the user get in
here well they open up a mainframe
emulator
on their desktop which shows them the
mainframe and then they go in they click
here and they put this number in there
and then they look up this customer and
then they switch this value to that
value and they say save and it's like
okay cool that rpa can do and we can do
that quite easily and we don't need to
talk about apis and we don't need to
talk about special access or doing
queries that makes you know infosec very
scared
you know a great use case for that is
you know a bank
say they acquire a regional bank and
they say cool you're now part of our
bank but in your systems that are now
going to be a part of our systems
you have users that have this value
whereas in our bank that value is this
value here so now we have to go and
change for 30 000 customers
this one field to make it line up with
our systems
traditionally you would get a you know
extract transform load tool and etl tool
to kind of do that but for 30 000
customers that might be below the
threshold and this is banking so it's
very regulated and you have to be very
very intentional about how you
manipulate and move data around
so
what do we have to do okay we have to
hire 10 contractors for six months and
literally what they're going to do eight
hours a day
is go into the mainframe through the
simulator and
customer by customer
they're going to go change this value
and hit save and they're looking at an
excel spreadsheet that tells them what
customer to go into and that's going to
cost x amount of money and x you know
for six months or what we could do is
just
build a rpa solution a bot essentially
that goes and for each line of that
excel
spreadsheet it repeats this one process
open up mainframe emulator navigate into
the customer profile and then change its
value and then shut down and repeat and
it can do that in one week
and can be built into
that's the dream use case for rpa and
that's really kind of a where it would
shine so it sounds like the
best use case for it is
an old system a mainframe system in
cobalt maybe uh doesn't have an api and
so
it makes sense to rather than
go okay how can we get directly into the
database or you know how can we build on
top of it let's just go through the
user interface that exists but just
automate that process
and
you know the example you gave it sounds
very
very well defined you're going to log in
and you're going to put in maybe this id
here's the fields you want to get back
and you're going to save those and you
didn't have to make any
real decisions i suppose in terms of do
i need to click this thing or this thing
it's always going to be the same path to
get there
exactly and that's really you need to be
disciplined about your use cases and
what those look like and you can broadly
say use case that i'm going to accept
has these features and one of the best
ways to do that is say it has to be a
binary decision process which means
there is no dynamic
or interpreted decision that needs to or
information that needs to be
made exactly like that use case it's
very binary either is or it isn't you go
in you journey into there and you change
that one thing and that's it there's no
oh well this information says this which
means then i have to go do this
once you start getting in those if else
processes you're going down a rabbit
hole and it could get very shaky and
that introduces extreme instability in
what you're trying to do and also really
expands your development time because
you have to capture these processes and
you have to say okay tell me exactly
what we need to build the spot to do and
for binary decision processes that's
easy go in here do this but
nine times out of ten as you're trying
to
address this and solution for it you'll
find those
uncertainties you'll find these things
where the business says oh well yeah
that happens you know 1 times out of 10.
and this is what we need to do and it's
like well that's going to break the bot
you know 9 times out of 10 this slot's
going to fall over this is now where we
start getting into the machine learning
and ai
realm and why rpa
is classified sometimes as a subset of
the ai or machine learning field
or is a pattern within that field
is because now that you have this bot or
this software that enables you to do a
human process
let's enable that bot to now do decision
making processes where it can interpret
something and then do something else
because
while we can just do a big if else tree
to kind of address every capability
you're never going to be able to do that
and also it's it's just a really heavy
bad way to build things
so instead let's throw in some machine
learning capability where it just can
understand what to do
and that's you know that's the next
level of rpa application
is okay we've got it we've gone through
our organization we found every kind of
binary thing that can be replaced with
an rpa bot
okay now what are the ones that we said
we couldn't do because it had some of
that decision making
that required too much of a dynamic
intelligence behind it and let's see if
we can address those now that we have
this and so that's the 2.0
in rpa is addressing those non-binary
paths i would argue
that especially in organizations
that are big enough to justify bringing
in an rpa solution to
solve for their processes they have
enough binary processes binary decision
processes
to keep them busy
some people kind of get caught up in
trying to write out the gate say we need
to throw some machine learning we need
to make these bots really capable
instead of just saying well we've got
plenty of work just
changing the binary processes or
addressing those let's just be
disciplined and take that approach i
will say
towards rpa and bots
the best solution or the only solution
when you talk about building a bot
is the one that you eventually turn off
so you can say i built a bot that will
go into our mainframe system and update
this value and that's successful i would
argue that's not successful when that
bot is successful is when you can turn
it off because there's an enterprise
solution that addresses it and you don't
have to have this
rpa bot that lives over here and does it
instead your enterprise capability now
affords for it
and so that's really i think a
successful bot or a successful rpa
solution is you've been able to take
away the pain point or that human
process
until
it can be correctly
addressed by your systems that everyone
uses from
the business perspective you know what
are some of the limitations or long-term
problems with leaving an rpa solution in
place that's a
that's a good question from the business
there isn't it's solved for
leaving it in place is other than just
servicing it and supporting it there's
no real issue there especially if it's
an internal system like a mainframe you
guys own that if it changes you'll know
it if it changes
it's probably being fixed or addressed
so there's no problem however that's not
the only application for rpa
let's talk about another use case here
your organization
uses
a bank
and you don't have an internal way to
communicate it your user literally has
to go to the bank's website login and
see information that the bank is saying
hey this is your stuff right the bank
doesn't have an api for that service
because that would be scary for the bank
they say we don't want to expose this to
another service so the human has to go
in there log in look at maybe a pdf and
download it and say oh okay so
that happens in a browser so it's it's a
newer technology this is in our
mainframe built in 1980
it's you know browser based it's in the
internet and all that but that's still a
valid rpa
application right it's a human process
there's no api there's no easy
programmatic way to solution for it it
would require the bank and your it team
to get together and you know hate each
other and figure out why this is so hard
so let's just throw a bot on it that's
going to go and log in download this
thing from the bank's website and then
send it over to someone else and it's
going to do that all day every day
that's a valid application and then
tomorrow the bank changes its logo and
now my bot is it's confused stuff has
shifted on the page it doesn't know
where to click anymore
so you have to go in and update that bot
because
sure enough that bank's not going to
send out an email to you and say hey by
the way we're upgrading our website in
two weeks it's not going to happen
you'll know after it's happened so
that's where you're going to upgrade the
bot and
that's the indefinite use of rpa is
going to have to keep until someone else
decides to upgrade their systems and
provide for a programmatic solution that
is completely outside the capability of
your organization to change and so
that's where the business would say we
need this indefinitely
it's not up to us and so that is an
indefinite solution that would be valid
right you can keep that going for 10
years as long i would say you probably
need to get a bank that maybe meets your
business needs a little easier but it's
valid and that would be a good way for
the business to say yes this needs to
keep running forever until it doesn't
you brought up the case of where the web
page changes and the bot doesn't work
anymore specifically you're giving the
example of finance and i feel like it
would be
basically catastrophic if the bot is
moving money to somewhere it shouldn't
be moving
because the ui has moved around or the
button's not where it expects it to be
and i'm kind of curious what your
experience has been with that sort of
thing you need to set organizational
thresholds and say something this
impacting or something that could go
this wrong it is not acceptable for us
to solve with rpa even though we could
do it it's just not worth it some
organizations say that's anything that
touches customer data healthcare and
banking especially to say yeah we have a
human process where the human will go
and issue refunds to a customer and that
could easily be done via rpa solution
but it's fraught
with what if it does something wrong
it's literally going to impact
someone somewhere their monies
or their security or something like that
that definitely should be part of your
evaluation and as an organization you
should set that up early and stick to it
and say nope this is outside our purview
even we can do it it has these things so
i guess the answer to that is you should
never get to that process
but and now we're going to talk about i
guess the actual
nuts and bolts of how our pa solutions
work
and how they can be made to not action
upon stuff when it changes or if it does
so
rpa software by and large operates by
exposing the operating system or the
browsers
underlying
models and interpreting them right so
when we talk about something like a
mainframe emulator
you have your rpa software
on microsoft windows it's going to use
the com the component operating model to
see what is on the screen what is on
that emulator it's going to expose those
objects to the software and say you can
pick these things and click on that and
do that when we're talking about the
browser what the rpa software is looking
at
is not only the com the component object
model there which is the browser
itself but then it's also looking at the
dom the document object model that is
the web page that is being served
through the browser and it's exposing
that and saying these are the things
that you can touch or
operate on and so when you're building
your
bots what you want to make sure is that
the uniqueness of the thing that you're
trying to
access
is something that is truly unique and if
it changes
that one thing that the bot is looking
for will not change so let's go back to
the banking website right we
go in and we launch the browser
and the bot is sitting there waiting for
the operating system to say this process
is running which is what you wanted to
launch
and it is in this state the bot says
okay i'm expecting this kind of com to
exist i see it does exist it's this
process and it has this kind of name and
cool chrome is running okay let's go to
this website
and after i've typed this in i'm going
to wait and look at the
dom
and wait for it to return this expected
web page name but they could change
their web page name the title of it
right they can say one day it can say
hello welcome to this bank and the next
day it says bank website all of a sudden
your bot breaks it no longer is
finding what it was told to expect so
you want to find something unique
that will never change
with that conceivably and so you find
that one thing on the dom on the banking
website you know this element or this
tag
says okay there's no way they're
changing that and so it says cool the
page is loaded now click on this field
which is login okay you want to find
something unique on that field that
won't change when they upgrade you know
from bootstrap to this kind of you know
ui framework that's all well and good
that's what we call the happy path it's
doing this perfectly now you need to
define what it should do when it doesn't
find these things which is not keep
going or find similar it's
it needs to fail
fast and gracefully and pass on that
failure to someone and not keep going
and that's kind of how we prevent that
scary use case where it's like
okay it's gone in it's logged into the
bank website now it's transactioning
bad things to bad places that we didn't
program it for it well you unfortunately
did not specify in a detailed enough way
what it needs to look for and if it
doesn't find that it needs to break
instead of saying no this is close
enough and so in all things software
engineering it's that specificity it's
that detail that you need to hook on to
and that's also where when we talk about
this being a low code no code solutions
that sometimes rpa is marketed to the
business it's just so often not the case
because yes it might provide a very user
business friendly interface for you to
build bots but the knowledge you need
to be able to ensure stability and
accuracy to build the bots is a
familiarity that's probably not going to
be had in the business it's going to be
had by a developer who knows what the
dom and com are and how the operating
system exposes
services and processes and how
javascript especially when we're talking
about single page apps and react where
you do have this very reactive dom
that's going to change you need to be
fluent with that and know not only how
html tags work and how css will change
stuff on you and classes but also how
clicking on something on a single page
app as simple as a username input field
will dynamically change that whole dom
and you need to account for it so it is
traditionally not as easy as saying oh
the business person can just click click
click click and there we have a bot
you'll have a bot but it's probably
going to be breaking quite often it's
going to be inaccurate in its execution
this is a business friendly
user-friendly non-technical tool
and i launch it and it says what do you
want to do and it says let me record
what you're going to do you say cool and
then you go about you open up chrome and
you type in the browser and then you
click here click there hit send and then
you stop recording the tool says cool
this is what you've done well i have yet
to see a solution that is able to
not need further direction or defining
on that process you still should need to
go in there
and say okay yeah you recorded this
correctly but you know you're not
interpreting correctly or as accurate as
you need to that field that i clicked on
and if you know anybody hits you know
f12 on their keyboard while they have
chrome open and they see how the dom is
built especially if this is using kind
of any kind of template web page
software it's going to have a lot of
cruft
in that html so while yes the recording
did correctly see that you clicked on
the input box what it's actually seen is
that you actually clicked on the
div that is four level scoped above it
or is the parent and there are other
things within that as well and so the
software could be correctly clicking on
that later but other things could be in
there and you're going to get some
instability so the human or the business
bot builder the
roboticists i guess would need to say
okay listen we need to pare this down
but it's even beyond that
there are concepts that you can't get
around
when building bots
that are unique to software engineering
as a concept and even though they're
very basic
it's still sometimes hard for the
business user to they still have to
learn that
and i'm talking
concepts as simple as for loops
or loops in general where
the business of course has knowledge of
what we would call a loop but they
wouldn't call it a loop and it's not as
accurately defined so they have to learn
that and it's not as easy as just saying
oh yeah do a loop and the business will
say well what's a loop like i know
conceptually what a loop could be like a
loop in my when i'm tying my shoe but
when you're talking about loop that's a
very specific thing in software and what
you can do and when you shouldn't do it
and that's something that these no
matter how good your
low code no code solution might be
it's going to have to afford for that
concept and so a business user is still
going to have to have some
lower level capability to apply those
concepts and have yet to see anybody be
able to get around that in their rpa
solutions so in your experience even
though these vendors may sell it as
being a tool that anybody can just sit
down and use but then you would want a
developer to sit with them or see the
result and try and figure out okay what
do you really want this code to do not
just sort of these broad strokes that
you were hoping the tool was gonna take
care of for you that's exactly right and
that's how every organization
will come to that realization pretty
quickly
the head of the game once have said okay
we need to have a really good
coe structure to this robotic operating
model where we can have a software
engineering developer capability that
sits with the business capability and
they can
marry with each other other businesses
who may take these vendors at their word
and say it's a low code meant for
business
ip just needs to make sure it's on
and accessible and then our business
people are just going to go in there and
do this they find out pretty quickly
that they need some technical guidance
to go in because they're building
unstable or inaccurate bots and whether
they come to that sooner or later they
always come to that and they realize
that okay there's a technical capability
and this is not just rpa
this is the story of all low code no
code solutions that have ever existed
it always comes around that while this
is a great interface for doing that and
it's very easy it makes concepts easy
every single time there is a technical
capability that needs to be afforded for
the web browser you mentioned the dom
which is how we typically interact with
applications there but for native
applications you briefly mentioned
com and i was wondering
when someone is
writing you know a bot what are the
sorts of things they see or what are the
primitives they're working with like is
there a name attached to each button
each text field things like that
wouldn't that be a great world to live
in
so there's not and as we build things in
the dom people get a lot better we've
seen people are getting much better
about using uniqueness when they build
those things so that they can latch on
to when things were built for the com
you know on.net for
os no one was like oh yeah we're going
to automate this or you know we need to
make this so that this button here is
going to be unique from that button over
there on the com it didn't care
different name so yeah that is sometimes
a big issue when you're using an rpa
solution you say okay cool
look at this
calculator app
and okay it's showing me the component
object model that this was built that's
describing what it's looking at but
none of these nodes have a name they're
all you know node 1 node 1.1 node 2 or
whatnot or button is just button and
there's no uniqueness around it and that
is
you see a lot of that in legacy older
software
legacy is things built in 2005 2010. you
do see that and that's the difficulty
at that point you can still solve for
this but what you're doing is you're
using send keys so instead of saying
okay rpa software open up this
application and then look for this this
object in the com and click on it it
can't there is no uniqueness so what you
say is just open up this software and
then just hit tab three times and that
should get you to this one place that
was not unique but we know
if you hit tab three times it's gonna
get there now that's all well and good
but there's so many things that could
interfere with that and break it and
there's no context for the bot to grab
onto to verify okay i am there so any
one thing you could have a pop-up which
essentially hijacks your send key
right and so the bot yes absolutely hit
tab three times and it should be in that
one place it thinks it is and it hits
enter but in between the first and
second tab a pop-up happened and now
it's latched onto this other process
it's enter and all of a sudden outlook's
opening bot doesn't know that but it's
still going on and it's going to enter
in some financial information
into oops an email that it launched
because it thought hitting enter again
would do so that's where you get that
instability there are other ways around
it or other solutions and this is where
we get into the you're using lower level
software engineering solutioning instead
of doing it exactly how the user does it
when we're talking about the operating
system in windows there are a ton of
interop services and assemblies that a
rpa solution can access so instead of
cracking open excel double clicking on
excel workbook waiting for it to load
and then reading the information putting
information in you can use the you know
the office 365 or whatnot the
interop service assembly and say hey
launch this workbook without the ui
showing it attach to that process that
you know it is and then just send to it
using that assembly send information
into it and the human user can't do that
it can't manipulate stuff like that but
the bot can and it it's the same ends as
the human user is trying it's much more
efficient and stable because the ui
couldn't afford for that kind of
stability so that would be a valid
solution but at that point you're really
migrating into
a software engineering it developer
solution of something that you were
trying not to do that for
so why not just go and solve for it with
an enterprise or programmatic solution
in the first place so that's the balance
earlier you're talking about
the rpa needs to be something that the
person is able to do and it sounds like
in this case
i guess there still is a way for the
person to do it they can open up the
excel sheet and they can still achieve
the same ends yep right it's just that
the way the rpa tool is doing it is
different right and more efficient and
more stable certainly especially when
we're talking about excel you have an
excel with you know 200 000 lines
just opening that that's your day that's
going to excel is just going to take its
time opening and visualizing that
information for you whereas you know an
rpa solution doesn't even need to crack
that open it can just send data right
directly to that workbook
and that's a valid solution and again
some of these processes it might be just
two people at your organization that are
essentially doing it so it's you know
you don't really it's not at a threshold
where you need an enterprise solution
for it but
they're spending 30 minutes of their day
just waiting for that excel workbook to
open
and then manipulating the data saving it
and then oh their computer crashed
so you can do an rpa solution it's going
to be to essentially build for a more
efficient way of doing it and that would
be using the programmatic solution but
you're right it is doing it in a way
that a human could not achieve it and
that again is
where the discipline and the
organizational aspect of this comes in
where it's saying is that acceptable is
it okay to
have it do things in this way
that are not human but achieving the
same ends and
if you're not disciplined
that creeps
and all of a sudden you have a rpa
solution that is doing things in a way
that the whole reason to bring that rpa
solution in is to not have something
that did something like that and that's
usually
where the
stuff falls apart it all of a sudden
perks their head up and says wait i have
a lot of connections coming in from this
one computer doing stuff very quickly
with a you know sql query
it's like what is going on it's all of a
sudden someone built a bot to
essentially do a programmatic connection
and it's like you should not be who gave
you those permissions who did this shut
down everything that is rpa here until
we figure out what you guys went and did
so that's the dance
it's almost like there's this hidden api
or there's this api that you're not
intended to use
but in the process of trying to automate
this thing you use it and then if your
it's not aware of it then things just
kind of spiral out of control
exactly right so a use case of that
would be
we need to get california
tax information on alcohol sales we need
to see what each county
taxes for alcohol to apply to something
and so today the human users they go
into the california you know tobacco
wildlife whatever website and they go
look up stuff
and okay that's very arduous let's throw
a bot on that let's have a bot do that
well the bot developers smart person
knows their way around google and they
find out well california has an api for
that instead of the bot cracking open
chrome it's just going to send this rest
api call
and it's going to get information back
and that's awesome and accurate and way
better than anything but now all of a
sudden
it sees connections going in and out all
of a sudden it's doing very quickly and
it's getting information coming into
your systems that in a way that you did
not know was going to be happening and
so while it is all well and good it's a
good way for
the people whose job it is to protect
yourself or know about these things to
get very angry rightly so that this is
happening
that's an organizational challenge and
it's an oversight challenge and it's a
it's a developer challenge because
what you're getting into is the problems
with having two technical people
build these rpa bots
right so on one hand we have business
people who are told hey just crack this
thing open and build it
and it's like well they don't have
enough technical fluency to actually
build a stable bot because they're just
taking face value on the other hand you
have software engineers or developers
that are very technical that say oh this
process yeah okay i can build a bot for
that but what if i used you know these
interop services assemblies that
microsoft gives me and i can access it
like that and then i can send an api
call over here and while i'm at it i'm
gonna you know i'm just gonna spin up a
server
just on this one computer
that can do this
when the bot talks to it and so you have
the opposite problem now you have
something that is just not at all rpa
it's just using the tool to you know
manipulate stuff programmatically
so as a part of all this
is using the same credentials as a real
user right you're logging with a
username and password if the form
requires something like two-factor
authentication or you know or something
like that like how does that work since
it's not an actual person there right so
in a perfect world you're correct a bot
is a user i know a lot of times you'll
hear say people will be like oh i i have
20 rpa bots what they're usually saying
is i have 20 automations that are being
run for separate processes
with one user's credentials on a vdi so
you're right they are using a user's
credentials with the same permissions
that any user that does that process has
that's why it's easy
but now we have these concepts like
two-factor authentication which every
organization is using that should
require something that exists outside of
that bot user's environment and so how
do you afford for that in a perfect
world it would be a service account not
a user account and service accounts are
governed a little differently a lot of
times service accounts have much more
stringent rules but also allow for
things like password resets not a thing
or two-factor authentication is not a
thing for those so that would be the
perfect solution
but now you're dragging in i t so you
know if you're not structurally set up
for that that's going to be a long slog
so
what you would want to do some people
actually literally have a will have a
business person that has their two
factor off for that bot user on their
phone and then just you know they'll
just go in and say yeah that's me
that's untenable
[Music]
so sometimes what a lot of these like
microsoft for instance allow you to do
is to install a two-factor
authentication
application
on your desktop so that when you go to
log in a website and says hey
type in your password cool okay give me
that code that's on your two-factor auth
app the bot can actually launch that app
copy the code and paste it in there and
be on its way but you're right now
you're having to afford for things that
aren't really part of the process you're
trying to automate
they are the incidentals that also
happen and so you have to build your bot
to afford for those things and interpret
oh i need to do two-factor
authentication
and a lot of times especially if you
have a
entirely business
focused rpa robotic operating model they
will forget about those things or find
ways around them that the bot isn't
addressing like having the authenticator
app on their phone that's um stuff that
definitely needs to be addressed and
sometimes is only found at
run time like oh
it's asking for login and when i
developed it i didn't need to do that
because i had you know the cookie that
said you're good for 30 days but now oh
no
yeah you could have two factor you could
have it asking you to check your email
for a code there could be a fraud
warning there's like all sorts of you
know failure cases that can happen yeah
exactly and those things are when we
talk about third-party vendors
third-party provider vendors like going
back to the banking website if you don't
tell them that you're going to be using
a bot to get their information or to
interface with that website you're
setting yourself up for a bad time
because they're going to see that kind
of at runtime behavior
that is not possible at scale by a user
so you run into that issue at runtime
but then you're correct there are other
things that you might run into at
runtime that are not again part of the
process the business didn't think that
that was part of the process it's just
something they do
that actually the bot has to afford for
that's part of the journey
in building these when you're building
these bots what are the types of tools
that you've used in the past are these
commercial packages are these open
source like what does that ecosystem
look like yeah in this space we have
three big ones which is automation
anywhere
uipath
and blue prism those are the rpa
juggernauts providing this software
to the companies that need it and then
you have smaller ones that are
trying to get in there or provide stuff
in a little different way
and you even have now
big juggernauts that are trying to
provide for it like microsoft with
something like power automate desktop so
all of these
say three years ago all these software's
existed or all these
rpa solution softwares existed or
operated in the same kind of way where
you would install it on your desktop
and it would provide you a studio to
either record
or define
originally the process that was going to
be automated on that desktop when you
pushed play and they all kind of exposed
or operated in the same way they would
interpret the com or the dom that the
operating system provided things like
task scheduler have traditionally
exposed and they all kind of did that in
the same way their
value proposition and their software was
the orchestration capability and the
management of that so i build a bot to
do this jim over there built a bot to do
that okay this rpa software not only
enabled you to define those processes
but what their real value was is they
enable a place where i can say this
needs to run at this time on this
computer and it needs to you know i need
to be able to monitor it and it needs to
return information and all that kind of
orchestration capability
now all of these rpa solutions actually
exist in the like everything else in the
browser so instead of installing you
know the application and launching it
and whatnot and the orchestration
capability being installed on another
computer that looked at these computers
and ran stuff on them now it's it's all
in the cloud as it were and they are in
the browser so i go to
wherever my rpa solution is in my
browser
and then it says okay cool you still
need to install something on the desktop
where you want the spot to run
and it deploys it there but i define and
build my process in the provided browser
studio and then we're going to give you
a capability to orchestrate
monitor and receive information on those
things that you have those bots that you
have running
and then what they're now providing as
well as the ability to tie in other
services to your bot so that it has
expanded capability so i'm using
automation anywhere and i've built my
bot and it's going and it's doing this
or that and automation anywhere says hey
that's cool wouldn't you like your bot
to be able to do ocr
well we don't have our own ocr engine
but you probably as an enterprise do
just use you know use your cofax ocr
engine or
hey if you're really high speed why
don't you use your azure cognitive
services capability we'll tie it right
into our software so when you're
building your bot instead of just
cracking open a pdf and
send key control c send key control v to
do stuff instead we'll use your ocr
engine that you've already paid for to
understand stuff and so that's how they
expand what they're offering into
addressing more and more capabilities
but now we're migrating into a territory
where it's like well things have apis
why even build a bot form you know you
can just build a program that uses the
api and the user can drive this and so
that's
where people kind of get stuck they're
using rpa on something that just as
easily provides for a programmatic
solution as opposed to an rpa solution
but because they're in their rpa mode
and they say we can use a bot for
everything they don't even stop and
investigate and say hey
wouldn't this be just as easy to
generate a react app and let a user use
this
because it has an api and it can just as
easily monitor and support that because
it's in an azure resource bucket that's
where an organization needs to be
clear-eyed and say okay at this point
rpa is not the actual solution
we can do this just as easy over here
and let's pursue that the experience of
making these rpas it sounds like you
have this browser-based ide
there's probably some kind of drag and
drop setup and then you mentioned
javascript so i suppose does that mean
you can kind of dive a little bit deeper
and if you want to set up specific rules
or loops you're actually writing that in
javascript yeah so not necessarily so
again the business does not know what an
ide is it's a studio um but you're
correct it's an id
whether we're talking about blue prism
or uipath or automation anywhere they
all have a different flavor of what that
looks like and what they enable
traditionally blue prism
gave you a studio that was more
shape based where you are using uml
shapes to define or describe your
process and then there you are whereas
automation anywhere traditionally used
essentially
lines or descriptors so i say hey
i want to open this file and your studio
would just show a line that said open
file you know although they do now all
of them have a shape based way to define
your process go here you know here's a
circle which represents this let's do
that or a way for you to kind of more
creatively define it in a like a
text-based way when we talk about
javascript or anything like that
they provide predefined actions all of
them saying i want to open a file or
execute this that you can do but all of
them as well
at least last time i checked also allow
you for a way to say i want to
programmatically run something i want to
define and since they're on the browser
it is you know javascript that you're
going to be saying hey run this
javascript run this function previously
things like automation anywhere would
let you
write stuff in.net essentially to do
that capability but again now
everything's in the browser
so yeah they do provide for a capability
to introduce more low-level capability
to your automation
that can get dangerous it can be
powerful and it can be stabilizing but
it can be a very slippery slope where
you have an rpa solution bot
that does this thing but really all it
does is it starts up and then executes
code that you bring like
what was the point in the first place
yeah and i suppose at that point then
anybody who knows how to use the rpa
tool but isn't familiar with that code
you wrote they're just
they can't maintain it anymore
you have lost business continuity and
this goes back to our it has to be
replicable or close as close to the
human process as you can make it because
that's going to be the easiest to
inherit and support that's one of the
great things about it whereas if you're
a
low level you know programmer or dev who
says i can easily do this with a couple
lines of
you know dotnet or you know typescript
or whatever and so the bot just starts
up and executes well unless someone that
is just as proficient comes along later
and says this is why it's breaking you
now have an unsupportable
business solution
that's bad juju
you have the software engineers who they
want to write code then you have
the people who are either in business or
in it that go i don't want to look at
your code i don't want to have to
maintain code yeah
so it's like you almost if you're a
software engineer coming in you almost
have to fight that urge to write
anything yourself and figure out okay
what can i do with the tool set and only
go to code if i can't do it any other
way that's correct and that's the
takes discipline
more often not not as fun as writing the
code where you're like i can do this and
this is really where the wheels come off
is you
went to the business the business said i
have this process very simple i need to
do this and you say cool i can do that
and then you're sitting there writing
code and you're like but you know what i
know what they really want to do and i
can write that now and so you've changed
the process and while it is and nine
times out of ten the business will be
like oh that's actually what we wanted
the human process was just as close as
we could get nothing else but you're
right that's exactly what we needed
thank you nine times out of ten they'll
love you for that but now you own their
process now you're the one that defined
it you have to do the business
continuity you have to document it and
when it falls over you have to pick it
back up and you have to retrain and
unless you have an organizational
capacity to say okay i've gone in and
changed your process i didn't automate
it i changed it now i have to go in and
tell you how i changed it and how you
can do it and so that unless you have
built your robotic operating model and
your team to afford for that
your developer could be writing checks
bigger than they can cache
even though this is a better capability
you've sort of touched on this before
and i think this is probably the last
topic we'll cover
but you've been saying how the end goal
should be
to
not have to use the rpas anymore and i
wonder if you have any advice for
how to approach that process and what
are some of the mistakes you've seen
people make i mean the biggest mistake
i've seen organizations make i think
is throwing the rpa solution out there
building bots and they're great bots and
they are creating that value they're
enabling you to save money and also
enabling your employees to go on and do
better more gratifying work
but then they say
that's it that's as far as we're gonna
think
instead of taking those savings and
saying this is for replacing this pain
point that we had to get a bot in the
first place to do so that's a huge
common mistake it's absolutely
understandable if i'm a
ceo or even you know the person in
charge of enterprise transformation it's
very easy for me to say
victory here's our money here's our
savings i've justified what we've done
go have fun instead of saying we need to
squirrel this money away and give it to
the people that are going to change the
system so that definitely one of the
biggest things the problem with that is
that's not realized until years later
when they're like oh we're still
supporting these bots so it is up front
having a
turn off strategy when can we turn this
bot off
what is that going to look like does it
have a road roadmap that will eventually
do that and that i think is the best way
and that will define what kind of
processes you do indeed build bots for
is you go to i.t and say listen we've
got a lot of these user processes human
processes that are doing this stuff is
there anything on your roadmap that is
going to then replace that and they say
oh yeah you know in three years we're
actually going to be standing up our new
thing we're going to be converting and
part of our analysis of the solution
that we will eventually stand up will be
does it do these things and so yes in
three years you're good and you say cool
those are the processes i'm going to
automate and we can shut those off
that's your point of entry for these
things not doing that
leads to
bots running
and doing things
even after
there is a enterprise solution for that
and more often than not i would say
greater than five times out of ten when
we are evaluating a process to build a
bot for easily five times out of ten we
say well no actually you don't even need
to do this
our enterprise application can do this
you just need retraining because your
process is just old
and no one knew you were doing this and
so they didn't come in and tell you hey
you need to use this so that's really a
lot of times what the issue is and then
after that we go in and say okay no
there's no solution for this is
definitely a bot needs to do this
let's make sure number one that there
isn't a solution on the horizon in six
months to a year because otherwise we're
just gonna waste time but let's make
sure there is or at least i t or the
people in charge are aware that this is
something that needs to be replaced bot
or no bot and so let's have an exit
strategy let's have a turn off strategy
when you have applications that are
relatively
modern like you have a jira a service
now you know they must have some sort of
api and it may just be that nobody has
come in and told them you just need to
plug these applications together and so
kind of what you're hitting on and
surfacing is the future of rpa whereas
everything we're talking about is using
a bot to essentially bridge a gap moving
data from here to there that can't be
done programmatically accessing
something from here to there that can't
be done programmatically so we use a bot
to do it that's only going to exist for
so long legacy can only be legacy for so
long although
inconceivably because we had that big
cobalt thing
maybe longer than we'd all like but
eventually these things will be upgraded
and so
either the rpa market will get smaller
because there's less legacy out there
and so rpa as a tool and a solution will
become much more targeted towards
specific systems or we expand what rpa
is
and what it can afford for and so that i
think is more likely the case and that's
the future where bots or automations
aren't necessarily interpreting the com
and the dom and saying okay click here
do that but rather you're able to
quickly build bots that utilize apis
that are built in and friendly and so
what we're talking about there is things
like appian or mulesoft which are these
kind of api integrators
are eventually going to be classified as
rpa they're going to be within this
realm
and i think where you're seeing that at
least surfaced or moving towards is
really what microsoft's offering in that
where they have something called power
automate which essentially is just a
very user-friendly way
to access apis that they've built
or other people have built so i want to
go and i need to get information to
servicenow servicenow has an api yeah
your it can go in and build you a nice
little app that does a little rest call
to it or a rest api call to it gets
information back or
you can go in and you know use
microsoft's power automate and say okay
i want to access
service now and it says cool these are
the things you can do and i say okay i
just want to put information in this
ticket and we're not talking about get
or patch or put or anything like that
we're just saying ah that's what it's
going to do and that's kind of what
microsoft is offering i think that is
the new state of rpa is being able to
interface in a user-friendly way with
apis because everything's in the browser
to the point where you know microsoft's
enabling add-ins for excel to be written
in javascript which is just the new
frontier
so that's kind of going to be the future
state of this i believe so moving from
rpas being this thing that's going to
click through website click through a
desktop application instead it's maybe
more of this higher level tool where the
user will still get this i forget the
term you use but this tool to build a
workflow right yeah a studio okay and
instead of saying oh i want this to
click this button or fill in this form
it'll be i want to get this information
from servicenow and i want to send
a message using that information to
slack or to twilio or you're basically
talking directly to these different
services and just telling it what you
want and where it should go
that's correct so as you said
everything's going to have an api right
seemingly everything has an api
and so instead of us our rpa bots or
solutions being
ui focused they're going to be api
focused where it doesn't have to use the
user interface it's going to use the
other service and again the cool thing
about apis in that way is that it's not
directly connecting to your data source
it's the same as your ui for a user it
sits on top of it it gets the request
and it correctly interprets that and
does it the same thing with your ui
where i say i click here and wherever it
says okay yeah you're allowed to do that
go ahead so that's kind of the benefit
to that but to your point the user
experience for whether using a ui or api
to build a rpa bot it's going to be the
same experience for the user and then at
this point what we're talking about well
where's the value offering or what is
the value proposition of rpa and that's
orchestration and monitoring and data
essentially
we'll take care of hosting these for you
we'll take care of where they're going
to run uh giving you a dashboard things
like that that's 100 correct it's
providing a view into that thing and
letting the business say i want to no
code this and i want to be able to just
go in and understand and say oh i do
want to do that i'm going to
put these things together and it's going
to automate this business process that i
hate but is vital and i'm going to save
it the rpa software enables you to say
oh i saw they did that and i see it's
running and everything's okay in the
world and i want to turn it on or off
and so it's that seamless kind of
capability that that's what that will
provide and i think that's really where
it is and but really where it's going
it'll be interesting to see
when the rpa providers
switch to that kind of language
because currently and traditionally
they've gone to business and said we can
build you bots or no no your users can
build bots and that's the value
proposition they can go in and instead
of writing in excel where you had one
very very advanced user that was
building macros into excel with vba and
they're unknown to it or anybody else
instead you know build a bot for it and
so that's their business position today
instead it's going to shift and i'd be
interested to see when it shifts where
they say listen we can provide you a
view
into those solutions and you can
orchestrate them and oh here's the
studio that enables people to build them
but really what you want to do is give
that to your it and just say hey we're
going to go over here and address
business needs and build them but don't
worry you'll be able to monitor them and
at least say yeah okay this is going
yeah and that's a shift it sounds like
where
rpas currently you were talking about
how
when you're configuring them to click on
websites and gui's
you really do still need someone with
the software expertise to know what's
going on
but
maybe when you move over to
communicating with apis maybe that won't
be as important maybe somebody who just
knows the business process really can
just use that studio and get what they
need that's correct right because the
api only enables you to do what it
defines
so servicenow which does have a robust
api
it says you can do these things the same
as a user can only click a button that's
there that you've built and said they
can click and so that is you can't go
off the reservation as easy with that
stuff really what's going to become
prime or important is as no longer do i
actually have an oracle server
physically in my location with a
database instead i'm using oracle's
cloud capability which exists on their
own thing
that's where i'm getting data from what
becomes important about being able to
monitor these is not necessarily like oh
is it falling over or is it breaking
it's saying what information are you
sending or getting from these things
that are not within our walled garden
and that's really where
it or the infosec is going to be maybe
the main
orchestrator or owner of rpa because
they're going to be the ones to say you
can't get that you're not allowed to get
that information it's not necessarily
that you can't do it and you can't do it
in a dangerous way but it's rather i
don't want you transporting that
information or bringing it in so that's
really what's going to change i think
that's a good place to wrap it up but is
there anything we missed or anything
else you want to plug before we go
no i think this is a pretty
comprehensive and i really enjoyed it
alex thanks for coming on the show no
thank you for having me it's been a joy
this has been jeremy jung for software
engineering radio thanks for listening
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook
twitter or through our slack channel at
scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening